<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An English translation of the Scottish Declaration against James Graham alias Marquess of Montrosse. Wherein many things are set right between the kingdom of Scotland and Commonwealth of England. With many observable passages, concerning the transactions with the late king, and their now declared king.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E597_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863544</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115748</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115748)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E597[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An English translation of the Scottish Declaration against James Graham alias Marquess of Montrosse. Wherein many things are set right between the kingdom of Scotland and Commonwealth of England. With many observable passages, concerning the transactions with the late king, and their now declared king.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Cuthbert, 1622-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock, for Francis Tyton, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the three daggers neer the inner Temple in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cuthbert Sydenham.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Scotland, Parliament.  A declaration of the Committee of Estates of the Parliament of Scotland, in vindication of their proceedings from the aspersions of a scandalous pamphlet, published by that excommunicate traytor, James Grahame. Under the title of a Declaration of James Marques of Montrosse, &amp;c. Printed in the year, 1649.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 2. 1649"; the 50 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Montrose, James Graham, --  Marquis of, 1612-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament. --  Declaration of the Committee of Estates of the Parliament of Scotland, in vindication of their proceedings from the aspersions of a scandalous pamphlet, published by that excommunicate traytor, James Grahame.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115748:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Engliſh Tranſlation OF THE Scottiſh Declaration AGAINST JAMES GRAHAM <hi>ALIAS Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Montroſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein many things are ſet Right between the Kingdom of Scotland and Commonwealth of England.</p>
            <p>With many Obſervable Paſſages, concerning the Tranſactions with the late King, and their now Declared King.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 12.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The words of the wicked are to lye in wait for blood, but the mouth of the upright ſhall deliver them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the three daggers neer the inner <hi>Temple</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115748:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115748:2"/>
            <head>AN Engliſh Tranſlation OF THE Scottiſh Declaration Againſt <hi>James Graham,</hi> alias Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WEre it not that the <hi>Glory and Honor of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of England,</hi> and theſe <hi>great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of Divine Wiſdom and Providence,</hi> are more principally beſmeared in this <hi>Declaration,</hi> then the perſon or party of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> I ſhould ſoon conſent with them, in the beginning of that <hi>Paper,</hi> That as they think others may well wonder they ſhould take pains to anſwer him, ſo much more that any one ſhould undertake to vindicate or apologiſe for his perſon or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115748:3"/> He, with the reſt of his party, can never be too much abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>true Liberties</hi> are mentioned, being the moſt deſperate engaged Inſtruments of carrying on the deſign of miſery to the three Nations.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing the whole ſtrain and ſcope of that <hi>Declaration</hi> is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on the <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> who are the true and lawful Heirs and Succeſſors of the <hi>Mercies</hi> and <hi>Providences of God to this Nation,</hi> and not ſo much againſt <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Party,</hi> though they make his Paper the occaſion of the <hi>Diſcourſe;</hi> I ſhall take liberty, with a ſerious warineſs, of giving any offence to the honeſt and godly party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſet ſome things right in that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> and vindicate the late honeſt and juſt <hi>Proceedings</hi> of our <hi>Parliament,</hi> to maintain yet the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between us and our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> almoſt quite broken by the <hi>Malignant Intereſt</hi> in that <hi>Nation,</hi> that while we keep evening reckoning we may be long friends, and that in their excuſing themſelves they may not ſo accuſe us before our and their Enemies, and ſo be devoured by them both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>But before I come to the <hi>Declaration</hi> it ſelf, I cannot paſs by ſome things which paſs up and down, leſs diſcernable, which are matter of the greateſt wonderment unto rational and ſober men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the heighth of their Zeal and Indignation ſhould be vented on <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> calling him <hi>Excommunicated Traytor, That viperous Brood of Satan, &amp;c.</hi> and yet ſtill keep up their eſteem of the late <hi>King,</hi> and their calling him, <hi>His ſacred Majeſty,</hi> with many ſuch <hi>clawing expreſſions,</hi> abhorring the leaſt thought of diſhonor to him, when <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſſe</hi> only acted as his Servant, and all that ever he did, in the ſtrength of that <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> he received both from the Father and the Son. Let it be conſidered for what is <hi>Montroſſe</hi> proclaimed <hi>Traytor</hi> by the <hi>Committee of Estates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He muſt either be a <hi>Traytor</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> he was not, for he acted by his <hi>Commands,</hi> according to his <hi>will:</hi> It muſt be then againſt the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and then much more is the <hi>King</hi> the <hi>Traytor,</hi> who created him to that work, if that Rule in Logick be true, <hi>Quod efficit tale eſt magis tale;</hi> though it is true, the Inſtrument is not excuſed for the <hi>principal Agent,</hi> yet the <hi>principal Agent</hi> is moſt to blame. <hi>Montroſſe</hi> was but a puny Agent to other great Traytors that the <hi>King</hi> made, who hath made thouſands in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in that ſence, and yet he himſelf muſt not ſo much as be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115748:3"/> be thought on in ſuch a capacity.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Montroſſe</hi> never acted, <hi>King Charls</hi> would have made another <hi>Traytor;</hi> and when <hi>Montroſſe</hi> was ſuppreſt, and gone out of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and all the Traytors in both <hi>Nations</hi> under hatches, yet we found where the root of our miſery lay, and were put to it, and puſled more by the grand Traytors own perſon, then by all his Army and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Inſtruments beſides.</p>
            <p>God himſelf hath given out a Statute Law from Heaven not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the perſons of men in Judgment; and it's Juſtice and Equity to lay the ſaddle on the right horſe; yea the <hi>King</hi> himſelf was to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his plain actings according to his <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> who in the beginning of this War, thought it not only fit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and his Army <hi>Traytors,</hi> but both <hi>Houſes of Parliament,</hi> as thoſe that gave him the only Commiſſion and Power to that work. And it may well be wondered, that the <hi>Scots,</hi> who were wont to be men plain and broad enough in their expreſſions when they will, and have done ordinarily to our <hi>Parliament,</hi> and many honeſt and godly men, ſhould now complement ſo groſly, as to call the Servant <hi>Traytor,</hi> and the Maſter, under whoſe power he acts, <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>ſpotleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>But if the man ſuch blame muſt have,</l>
               <l>What's due to th' Maſter of the knave?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Do the <hi>Committee of Eſtates</hi> mean to revive that old Maxime in the the end of the War, that we fought againſt in the beginning?</p>
            <q>That the King can do no wrong, That he is not accountable to any but God, and ſo incapable of any Charge.</q>
            <p>Either lower <hi>Monarchy</hi> in your thoughts and pretences to it, or never ſolely tax theſe gallant and ſtout <hi>spirits,</hi> who act under it out of the true ſence of what you in words pretend, and who have wanted nothing to make them fully honorable, but a good <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Principle.</hi> It cannot chooſe but be a double grief to them, that they ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for doing their duty to him who is uncapable of guilt in commanding, and that they ſhould have not only part of the miſery, but the whole guilt, who were but Inſtruments, and he free that is the Efficient; as if the ſword ſhould be arraigned for Treaſon that kil'd the man, and the perſon that ſtruck the blow diſcharged.</p>
            <p>If <hi>England</hi> had not left off that method of Courtſhip and Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we had been as far to ſeek of our juſt <hi>Liberties,</hi> after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heading of theſe <hi>Traytors,</hi> which were thought moſt notorious, as we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115748:4"/> were at firſt; and let <hi>Scotland</hi> look unto it, if they make not better diſtinctions, they may find other kind of <hi>Traytors,</hi> more dangerous then <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> ſhortly entertained in <hi>Scotland</hi> with joy and accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. I have been the longer on this obſervation, to learn the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates</hi> to ſpeak plain Engliſh betimes, leſt they get that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tyranny that we have happily and hopefully freed our ſelves from, and we be troubled with a Scottiſh War; they are a little longer learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this leſſen then we are, being yet fain implicitely to hold forth what we practiſe, but muſt come to it ſhortly, when ſome vails are off, and they ſee both root and branch together among them: only it is pity that theſe which have been firſt in the War ſhould be laſt in enjoying the Peace: But that fault is not ours.</p>
            <p>The next thing which runs along the whole Paper, as the burthen of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> is, (and which I cannot paſs by) the great reflections they caſt on the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> and that honeſt party that joyns with them joyning them with <hi>Montroſſe</hi> together, as if they kept mutual correſpondency, calling them at every turn, <hi>The Sectarian Party, The now prevailing Party, Heretiques, Schiſmatiques,</hi> as if they meant to ſupple and make up their harſh expreſſions againſt <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſſes</hi> perſon, with his party, by inveighing on the <hi>Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and theſe which joyn with them, excommunicating them out of their affections and love, as they have done <hi>Montroſſe</hi> out of the Kirk. Expreſſions exceeding dangerous, and too much provoking, that when we ſhall call them, <hi>Our Dear Brethren,</hi> eſpecially after an Army came from them into our Nation to deſtroy (uſing the ſame expreſſions.) Had they but reflected on their condition but the laſt year, when <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lton</hi> was the prevailing party, and what ſort of people they were that ſet them free, and made the <hi>Committee of Eſtates</hi> the prevailing party, with the diſſolution of their whole <hi>Parliament,</hi> they might have fitted more handſom and tender expreſſions, at leaſt, if they meant to have kept up any brotherly Union and Correſpondence between the two <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth the gentle ſtreams of a River between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> ſo alter and change the nature of Tranſactions, that the purging of a <hi>Parliament in Engl nd,</hi> over grown with Malignant and Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant humours, ſhould be leſs lawful then the breaking up of one in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Or is the natural working out of diſtempers worſe then a violent diſſolution?</p>
            <p>It hath been the happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> for ſome few years, that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115748:4"/> 
               <hi>Parliament</hi> hath been the prevailing party, and why it ſhould be now our miſery after we have conquered our viſible Enemy to ſee our friends prevail, is too great a Paradox to be ſuddenly expounded: Some muſt be the prevailing party; and why not theſe that are? who have hated theſe complemental Compliances with the <hi>Royal Interest,</hi> and have followed the firſt Principles of the War, to the beſt advantage, for Peace. But I was very unwiſe to tax the <hi>Declaration</hi> with that as a fault, the expreſſing of which is our mercy: As I doubt not but they think of it concerning themſelves, that it's a happineſs to <hi>Scotland</hi> that this <hi>Committee of Estates</hi> is now the prevailing party, though it was brought in without any legal or orderly diſſolution of <hi>Hamiltons Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and <hi>Committee of Eſtates,</hi> and by theſe Inſtruments that they can now gratefully call <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> and <hi>Sectaries.</hi> But the ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the Sectarian party, and the prevailing party, ſets forth the mind of the <hi>Committee</hi> to the full. And yet what is meant by the Sectarian party, is yet a greater Riddle then all the reſt; for, ſet aſide the ſecret <hi>Placitum</hi> of the <hi>Committee of Eſtates,</hi> it ſtands without its ſignification in <hi>England,</hi> without it be a Title impoſed to divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween honeſt and conſciencious men, that ſome may raign.</p>
            <p>But it may be they have ſome ſecret and multiplyed meaning in this phraſe, that muſt be enquired into; if they call them the Sectarian party, becauſe they have juſtly divided the Kings Head from his Body, and ſo have made a Schiſm between <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> they ſhall willingly own the Title with a Crown of Juſtice, and glory in the head of it.</p>
            <p>But it may be they call them Sectaries, becauſe they have made a more exact diviſion of the true and right Engliſh Intereſt, and that of Scotland, and between new and old Malignants in the three Nations.</p>
            <p>Or it may be, they derive it from the word <hi>Sectari,</hi> becauſe they have more cloſely followed the ends and intentions of the Covenant, then the literall and ambiguous expreſſions in it, and have proſecuted the greateſt enemies of Reformation by Acts of Juſtice to their graves.</p>
            <p>But if by Sectaries the Committee mean theſe men that are of divers factions and parties, and intereſt in England, as we have cauſe to bewaile it, ſo we may in part thank ſome of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for it, who have caſt ſo many bones of diviſion among us, to ſet up the Royall, and their own intereſt, as the Parliament
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115748:5"/> have publikely declared in their Anſwer to the Scots Paper of March 13. 1647. p. 1. 2. complaining of the ſad diviſions among us, expreſſe themſelves, &amp;c. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the advancing of this deſign of the common enemy, the Commiſſioners of Scotland have for a long time made themſelves, or have been made by others very inſtrumentall, whilst forgetting the work they came about, and the true intereſt of thoſe from whom they came, have made it their work by their practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and purpoſes, to diſaffect the people of both Kingdomes unto the proceedings of the Parliament of England, and on the other hand to incline, and dispoſe them to the King, and his party upon terms apparently deſtructive to both Kingdoms.</hi> That it ſeems it's no new thing for the Committee to frame words of diviſion in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but I am loath to repent theſe old Quarrells, if there were not new occaſions given.</p>
            <p>But if they mean by Sectaries theſe which are given to blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Opinions contrary to the Goſpell, though there are but a few in compariſon ſo left of God, yet we will joyne with them, not only to write againſt, but weep, and lie in the duſt for any ſuch abominations, and we can never bewail enough theſe things, that on the one ſide formality and meer ſhaddowes of Religion ſhould be taken up, and all holineſſe be only outward and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and on the other ſide, that fancy and deluſion ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile to cheat men of their ſouls, and cloud the glory of the truths of Chriſt: But it's a great wrong to joyne in this, ſince the prevailing party with the Sectarian, whoſe hearts I doubt not but bleed as truly inwardly for theſe things, as they have expreſt an outward deteſtation of them, in burning ſome of their books, and caſting ſhame on their perſons; but as none of theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are vented in publike, but with publike Declaration againſt them, ſo theſe which are vented in private, are but by a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable and contemptible perſons, and (we bleſſe God) with little ſucceſſe at preſent.</p>
            <p>And I doubt not, if we can agree in civill Principles with our Brethren, we ſhall ſoon in Religion, in the Doctrine and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialls of it, wherein the life and power lies, and if we differ in Diſcipline, it will not be in the things themſelves, but in extent and latitude of its power, that there will be no more dſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but as of an Engliſh and Scottiſh Government of the Church.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115748:5"/>
            <p>I have onely ſurmized theſe things, that the Reader may take notice of the common deſign in the Declaration, which ſeems to be very ſtrange that in one Paper made againſt a great Delinquent, the Parliament of England (who have moſt oppoſed the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant intereſt) ſhould be ſpecially aimed at, and their tranſactions inſerted in the ſame Kalender; but it's well they cannot call them Traytors, we may poſſibly e're long ſee what new names we ſhall injoy, when <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> and <hi>Montroſſe</hi> ſhall both joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the honeſt party of Scotland, and when they have got a King, who will be his favourites in Scotland? I pray that the ſame names be not juſtly retorted on themſelves by that party which they are faine now to court with expreſſions of diſgrace on their beſt friends.</p>
            <p>But to the Declaration it ſelf, and the maine things <hi>Montroſſe</hi> layes as a charge on them, which they ſtrive to free themſelves from, I ſhall follow their own method, and give them their due in what ever is juſt and right, and excuſe them wherein they do not intangle themſelves.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing <hi>Montroſſe</hi> taxes them withall, to which they reply, is for hatching a Rebellion in their own Kingdome, with promoting the like in England, &amp; becauſe they are both of the ſame nature, or as the end and the means, the ſame Reply wil ſalve both; I need to comment little on this, but to improve it on the ſame grounds and reaſons: only this is worthy to be obſerved, that what we account our duty and ſafety, they account rebellion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day; that which the Committee calls their juſt defence, as they do well expreſſe it in the ſecond page: <hi>Did we offer to ſtir un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Religion and Juſtice, the main pillars of Government, were ſhaken, and neere to be overturned? and ſhall the ſtanding upon our defence for the preſervation of our Religion and Liberties be accounted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee how the juſt and righteous grounds of your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are interpreted, and that which you think honeſty is ſtill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led rebellion, though but in the firſt motions of it, much more in the propagated neceſſary actings of that principle; and you now ſee what ever gloſſe is put upon your tranſactions, you ſhall be no more free of Rebellion then England, but rather be accounted the firſt and principall powers in all the reſt of the acts, though
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115748:6"/> done by us, and it's well you and we have a clear conſcience, for elſe we ſhall not want Records and Remembrancers of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer actings, though never ſo honeſt and neceſſitous; and if you think it's only <hi>Montroſſe</hi>'s malice, you are as much miſtaken in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike, as he was in legall and juſt actings; he dare ſpeak nothing but what the King his Maſter firſt dictates: if you compare the Kings Pourtraicture in his laſt Book, and his thoughts of your Nation there, with his practiſes to you, you will not find it a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: And if your new King did not account you Rebells, he would ſoon have complied with you, his principles leading him to a union with any party, but thoſe that mean to make Religion and Liberty their intereſt; and whereas you call <hi>Montroſſe</hi> Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and he calls you Rebells, who ſhall decide the Controverſie between you, when your King himſelfe thinks the ſame, and you in your conſciences think him a Traytor? And hath not <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſſe</hi> more ground (as to the world) to call you Rebells, who will owne not only the ſame power, but the ſame perſons who have acted point-blank againſt what you call Juſtice, then you to call him Traytor, who acts (though it may be more violently under that power you account ſacred) &amp; cannot live without that perſon that he ſerves as his Soveraigne? We have found the miſery of dawbing with the King, we have changed oftentimes not onely our motions, but many times principles to win and gain him, but he never charged his, but alwayes gained by our retreats, and what ever plea we or our Brethren may have for the firſt ground of our actings, it's otherwiſe, nay quite contrary apprehended by the King and his Party; and to thoſe that know what nature is, or education, they can eaſily judge how hard it is to change the firſt idaea and impreſſion of things, eſpecially when it is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with glorious Prerogatives, and apprehenſions of ſelf-advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and in royall breſts it's commonly ſeen, that injuries and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts are written as in Marble, while reſpects and kindneſſes are thought due, and of neceſſity to be ſucceſſive, and onely valid <hi>&amp; hic, &amp; nunc,</hi> according to an immediate circumſtance and preſent conveniency: and if they will abſtract that which they call policy, and a little while look into the nature of things, they ſhall ſoon find that there is not a motion of the hearts either of the King of Malignants, or the Malignants themſelves chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115748:6"/> from what their firſt apprehenſion, onely they are fain tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough providence and deſign to complement with us, and then as our Brethren too groſſely do at preſent with them, untill they get as the Scots ſay, to be the prevailing party; but I know they are ſenſible enough of theafter-reckoning, notwithſtanding they ſum up at preſent.</p>
            <p>And therefore in vindication of themſelves and us, they honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ingeniouſly ſtate the firſt grounds of the quarrell both in England and Scotland, which is well done; and it were to be wiſht that it were imprinted on all our hearts in both Nations with a point of a diamond; and it had been happy theſe virgin, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted principles had been alwaies kept unto in Scotland. They tell us <hi>p.</hi> 3. that when they were living quietly and peaceably, a new Service Book was impoſed on them to introduce Popery, &amp;c. and relate the Kings invaſions of them for but refuſing it againſt their conſciences, charge him with breach of truſt after Articles given: And as to their conjunction with England, as their aſſiſtance was deſired, ſo they ſaw further cauſe and reaſon then formerly: <hi>p.</hi> 3. they notably expreſſe the pranks of the King and his adherents, not ſtaying in Scotland, but traverſing Ireland, in a bloody Rebellion, againſt thouſands of Proteſtants; who had the Kings Commiſſion, and with whom he afterwards made an Agreement, rather then ſubmit to any juſt condeſcentions of the Parliament, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of England, and Scotland, though he had declared them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Traytors, for their bloody maſſacres; having alſo entruſted divers Popiſh Commanders in his Armies, contrary to his firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, that no Papiſt ſhould be in armes, or about his perſon. Upon theſe, and ſuch like reaſons, they and we joyned together in Covenant. To which we may add his perfidious Treatings with us oftentimes, eſpecially at Brainford: his hatred of the Covenant, his impenitency, continued actings in a ſecond warre, more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then the former, with a thouſand more deſperate tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both by himſelf, and Son, and all theſe propagated and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued without any hope of remedy, but by loſing all the blood, and expence of an eight yeares warres, with danger and hazzard at the beſt for the future. All theſe are ſufficient grounds for honeſt men to look to themſelves at firſt, and defend themſelves in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and much more to provide for themſelves at laſt: Onely
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115748:7"/> the miſery is in the uſe, and application; The Scots can find enough to vindicate themſelves from rebellion at the firſt of theſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet can willingly taxe us at the end for doing the ſame things. They can juſtly (but upon a thought of feare, and danger in ſome unfit overtures) find ground to make uſe of the ſword to defend themſelves, and cut off their enemies in generall; and yet when the ſame things come to be heightened, and break out in a greater flame, and continued without hope of redreſſe, they will condemn us for ſtriking the laſt blow, upon the ſame and greater grounds, when they began the firſt; as if the continuation of the ſame cauſe more deſperately ſhould not produce more notable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; or that the modeſt and ſecret eſſayes of things ſhould bee more deſperate, then the ſtrenuous propagation, and proſecution of them, and that aggravated, and multiplied acts of tyranny ſhould be more veniall, then bare attempts, which may be eaſily reformed by maturer counſell. If the Kingdom of Scotland, and England had ſufficient ground to take up armes againſt the King at firſt, when the ſparks were but as under aſhes, much more ground had Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land when the flame was not onely broken out, but daily fed, and increaſed, to make uſe of theſe armes to extinguiſh the chief In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary. But conſcience, it ſeems, made the principle, and policy, and deſign the application. If they juſtifie the beginning of the work, we may well the end of it, on the ſame, yea more abſolute and neceſſitous grounds. However <hi>Montroſſe</hi> is deceived in both, yet we ſhould not put arguments into his hand, by parting the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which have been correſpondent to the ſame principle. Yet this is the happineſſe of England thorough mercy, that our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſhall have the ſcandall, or rather glory of the beginning of the warre, and we of the end, yet they will be as much, and more hated for what they acted firſt, then we for what we have done at laſt, having improved both their principles and our own, together with the Kings tyrannicall power, to our own ſafety, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ruine; while they complementing but with a name (which they will find to be, as moſt inſnaring, ſo like the name of the Beaſt which hath a myſtery of deceipt wrapt up in it) are not only like to be where they were, but in a far worſe condition then ever Scotland was in, if God ſuffer but that young Spark to King it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115748:7"/>
            <p>But to come to his more ſpeciall charges, which <hi>p.</hi> 4. they call his laſt, and main forgeries; they are reduced unto three heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That his late Majeſty being redacted to think on extreme courſes, did ingage us by a Treaty, and having got all aſſurance from us, did caſt himſelf into the hands of our Army, and that we contrary to all faith and paction ſold our Soveraigne. 2. That they now complotted his deſtruction, and begin on the ſame ſcore with his Son, declaring him King with proviſo's, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of all theſe charges they ſay there is not one word true; But that his late Majeſty was redacted to an extreme courſe. It were wel firſt to conſider, whether in a true ſenſe theſe are charges worth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving or anſwering; that is, firſt whether the delivery up of the King to the Parliament of England when in England, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any private treaty, or particular promiſe of any Officers, were not juſt, and their duty. 2. Whether the taking away by death, ſuch an implacable and gangren'd perſon, were any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotting his deſtruction, but a legall execution of juſtice; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the declaring his Son King with proviſo's be not juſt and fit, no King being fit to reigne, but he that meanes to compact for the ſafety and liberty of that Kingdome he is called to exerciſe that Office in.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing the Committee take all theſe as hainous and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous charges on them; I ſhall give the reader a particular account of each of them; not to confirm <hi>Montroſſes</hi> paper, but to cleer ſome things concerning our ſelves, and them, and let truth and reaſon reigne.</p>
            <p>In vindication of themſelves from the firſt, they ſpend ſeverall pages, and ſtrive to give a narrative of all proceedings in the Army and Parliament both in England and Scotland, from the time of his coming in to their Army in the moneth of May 1646. unto May 1647. with the many Declarations both of the King, and their Parliament concerning the end of his coming in to them, which I am loath to repeat, leaſt I give too much offence to our Brother, or puzzle the Reader with tranſcribing; onely give in what I know concerning the truth of the charge, and meet with ſome extravagancies in their Narrative.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115748:8"/>
            <p>For the firſt, Though I hate the charge as it comes out of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſſe's</hi> mouth, and under ſo unclean a hand, yet for truths ſake, and ſeeing they are not content to free themſelves, but to charge us, and mixe therewith many ominous reflections on this Nation, I ſhall preſent ſomething more then probable, that may make the penners of that Declaration think that though they have engroſt the Prerogative of impoſing names, yet they have not the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of truth in all they write. They ſay <hi>p.</hi> 5. that after many eſſaies for London, and the Sea, he came to the Scots Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acquainting thoſe that had the truſt, and the charge of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and ask (I hope to be reſolv'd) where was there any time or place for a Treaty here; and what were thoſe aſſurances that were given? Let it be but asked the Committee, whether <hi>Montrill</hi> the French Agent was not in the Scots quarters at Southwel, and <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſent many times, and what they did there, and the queſtion will ſoon be reſolv'd; the truth is, as <hi>Hudſon</hi> himſelf related, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to ſome of honeſty and integrity, that the King emploied <hi>Montrill</hi> for that end, and often ſent <hi>Hudſon</hi> to treat about his coming in, who came often unto three of the Lords, I will forbear to name them for his honour ſake, and propounded three Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions concerning the Kings ſecurity, and other things, which he preſt them to ſigne, but they refuſed to give any thing under their hands, leaſt it ſhould be diſcovered, but that it ſhould be as truly performed, as if they had done it; at which <hi>Hudſon</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that he would not truſt them with words, ſeeing they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the King ſo often before, and that he would never perſwade his Majeſty without ſome paper ſecurity, and confirmation, under their hands: but their particular Engagements were at laſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thorough the mediation and aſſurance of <hi>Montrill;</hi> and the General moreover ſaid, that he would willingly go on his knees to meet them; theſe things were the profeſt relation of <hi>Hudſons</hi> own mouth; now what the capitulations were, and how far ſecurity was given, I will not determin, but the world may judge they were not in a dream, as they profeſſe in their paper to the Parliament immediately on his coming into them, and that they need not be ſo abſolute in their challenges of any one to produce any teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or demonſtration for any ſuch overture; <hi>Hudſon</hi> very well knew what he came at Southwell for, and what he did there, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115748:8"/> this is faithfully his account from his own mouth, with many more circumſtances of a ſtrange nature, which out of love, and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I omit. Yea <hi>Hudſon</hi> would often ſay, when he heard that they denied any ſuch knowledge, with much vehemency, that they groſſely lied.</p>
            <p>I ſhall relate but one ſtory more, which makes it out of doubt; and it is a relation I heard with my own ears given in upon Oath, by one that had relation to the Bed-chamber, <hi>viz.</hi> that one night at New-caſtle the late King coming out into the preſence Chamber to ſupper, not very well pleaſed at ſomething concerning the Scots dealing with him, was reading in the window a Pamphlet that came out about that time, entituled, <hi>A game at Scotch, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> wherein many particulars were diſcovered about the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing away of <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> and <hi>Hudſon,</hi> and ſomething about his coming in at Southwell to the Scots Army; at which he was much pleaſed, and ſaid they were moſt truths: He turns about to Sir <hi>James Lumſdale</hi> then Governor of New-caſtle, who ſtood by with ſeverall Lords, and ſaith to him, you did not know of the conveighing away of theſe two, and he anſwered no, if it like your Majeſty: he turnes to one of the Lords (I take it it was the Lord <hi>Dumferlin</hi>) no nor you did not know (ſaith he) of my coming in to your Army at Southwell, and he anſwered no he did not; the King after his wonted manner ſwore thus, by God, but you did; I am ſorry I ſhould ſwear ſuch an Oath again in print, but it's law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe it's for the publique deciding a controverſie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of truth; that you have two Oaths, if the world will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Kings Oath, who knew well enough what was done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelf, and another Oath confirming that he heard him ſwear thus.</p>
            <p>But I leave it to the judicious Reader to conſider, I believe it was done but by ſome particular perſons, and very privately, that the Parliament of Scotland knew it not, and the fair delivery of him, with their quiet march out of England is ſufficient ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to us, and to acquit them for that private miſcarriage. I wiſh they had been as faithfull at the Iſle of Wight as they were with him then, and that they may come as fairly and honeſtly off from this King at Breda, as they did from his Father at New-caſtle.</p>
            <p>Onely I cannot but obſerve one paſſage (<hi>p.</hi> 13.) where though
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115748:9"/> we and all honeſt men will joyn iſſue with the Committee, that none can imagine they ſold the King for money, but did their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in delivering him up to the Parliament, yet I wonder they make the demonſtration of it to be that they onely got two hundred thouſand pounds of the Arrears due unto them for a very labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſervice, and as a part of the great expences they had been at by their expedition into England for the ends of the Covenant: two hundred thouſand pounds is not ſo ſmall a ſum to be given for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, eſpecially if they conſidered the vaſt expences England had been at firſt, and laſt, and what great ſums of money they received at ſeverall times from England, beſides the Aſſeſſement of the four Northern Counties, and free-quarter, which came to farre more (as it was audited by the Parliament) then the Scots pay, and arrears came unto: eſpecially if we conſider what two hundred thouſand pound ſterling is accounted in the Kingdom of Scotland; but moſt eſpecially, ſeeing it was for the ends of the Covenant, and that we muſt pay them for doing their duty, and that in ſo great ſums, and be ſlighted for our love, is ſtrange, we could give our brethren 300000. l. for but beginning to reſiſt Tyranny, though principally relating to themſelves, and think nothing of it, and ſince for but aſſiſting in a cauſe of common concernment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were equally engaged with us, and for following the ends of the Covenant, they have had firſt, and laſt <hi>viis &amp; modis,</hi> above a million of money in England, and yet they go about to leſſon our favours, and heighten their owne Engagements and ſervices for the Covenant, though all upon our ſcore: but theſe things are ſlips, and muſt be paſt by as leſſer Errataes that doe not ſpoile the ſenſe; I onely adde this, that never had Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſo much of Englands wealth, and treaſure in ſuch round ſums in all the Reigns of the Kings either of England or Scotland, as they have had from this Parliament, and it's bad parting with ſuch friends.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Charge is, <hi>That they have complotted the late Kings deſtruction;</hi> to wipe of which aſperſion, they labour as in the fire; and I ſhall freely acquit them only becauſe they think it a Charge of ſo hainous a nature to have any hand in that legal act of Juſtice on him, and inſinua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the guilt of it on us. I muſt crave leave to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate that act, as no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only moſt neceſſary, but juſt, and an act of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115748:9"/> moſt celeſtial and divine diſpoſal and import, as any civil act done in <hi>England</hi> ſince its firſt conſtitution.</p>
            <p>For the lawfulneſs of bringing Kings to Iuſtice, and to condemn them, if they be found Tyrants, its not ſo much as queſtioned in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Caſuiſts, and in reaſon if they may be depoſed for ill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as we have inſtances both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> they may be executed on the ſame ground, without we will take the notion of Kings in that large and vaſt capacity that the late deluded and blinded Royaliſts have uſed it, <hi>That the King is a creature only of Gods making, all other Magiſtrates being acknowledged to be the creature of the people but only Kings, and they exempted from, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent to any power but only Gods.</hi> And if <hi>Lex</hi> be <hi>Rex,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> proveth at large, and Kings are under and ſubject to Laws, why ſhould vve ſuppoſe them above puniſhment, when they are found the higheſt Tranſgreſſors of thoſe Laws? Grant them all that diety the Scripture inveſts them with, yet when they come to dye, it is as other men, it may be for the ſame offences, as well as in the ſame condition of nature; yea, it's againſt Reaſon and Nature (though through uſu ped cuſtom it hath got ſom credit) that all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſhould be liable to puniſhment, in caſe of mal-adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of th ir office, and only that one order excepted.</p>
            <p>But to come nigher home, and conſider what our firſt Arguments and Diſtinctions were of making a War againſt the King, and the ſame will hold for ſharpening the Sword now, and cutting more keenly, and cloſer to the root.</p>
            <p>The Royaliſts always told us, we ſinned in fighting againſt the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> and took up Arms againſt that pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r which God had made ſacred, and ſo called us Rebels againſt <hi>Gods Ordinances;</hi> we then in both Nations found out a diſtinction (which doubtleſs was proper and rational enough) of a politick and a perſonal capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the King, the one never dyed, and was in the ſupream Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> though the perſon was abſent, who was but a publique Officer of that power; and therefore anſwered, We fought not againſt his legal capacity, but his perſonal, commanding and acting thoſe things which were contrary to Law, and the good of the Kingdoms. Let us but improve this diſtinction to what is done in the execution of the late King. If there may be a ſeparation between the King and his Power and Office, and ſo he may be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115748:10"/> fought againſt, and all weapons of death taken up to oppoſe him, why is it more unlawful to ſeparate his Head from his Body by the ſame diſtinction? F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r what is his Perſon, when you abſtract his Power? or where will you find it but among the common rabble of mankind? Let <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> be conſidered without his publike capacity and what will become of then name <hi>King?</hi> All the while you fight againſt his perſonal capacity, which is but as <hi>Charls Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art,</hi> you fight againſt but an ordinary and common man; for it's the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> feare of him with ſuch an office that ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es him in more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry condition. The ſame Objecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of the Royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wil prove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him, as taking away his life for the ſame, and farther reaſons: for they rightly ſay, as you cannot conſider Kingly power without a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whom it is inveſted, but in a metaphiſicall abſtraction, ſo neither can you act againſt the perſon, without conſidering of him as one without the power, and ſo as a private man: if our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren can maintain the firſt, and hold it lawfull upon ill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or tyranny to ſeparate the perſon, and the office, we ſhall eaſily maintain the laſt, when he is publikely deveſted of all, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a common condition, to uſe him as an ordinary perſon in caſe of felony and treaſon: for his publike capacity was at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, when his perſon was at Oxford, when we beſieged him, and fought againſt him, ſo the ſame capacity was at Weſtminſter, when his body was on the Scaffold at White-Hall, paying unto Juſtice for his miſ-government, and tyranny; and we beheaded him as a Tyrant not as a King.</p>
            <p>Let our brethren find out ſome new diſtinctions, or els we are as far from being murtherers, as they from being Traytors and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, which are much of kin together.</p>
            <p>But farther as it is unqueſtionably lawfull on ſerious, and reall grounds to depoſe, and do juſtice on Kings, and Princes as other Magiſtrates, ſo never was there a greater, and more univerſal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of all reaſons and circumſtances, and a greater harmony of the Laws of nature, reaſon, prudence, and neceſſity to warrant any Act, then was found, and may be diſcerned in that Act of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice on the late King, it will be too large to repeat, let us onely rub up our memory, and wipe our eyes, and we may ſoon glance at that which may eaſily ſatisfie us.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115748:10"/>
            <p>Firſt, Let us but conſider the beginning of the actions and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of that perſon in Scotland, the inhumane promotion of that bloudy maſſacre in Ireland, which unto this day cannot chooſe but make a trembling in the ſouls and bodies of any tender heart, which the Scots themſelves freely charge him with in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Declaration, the groſſe, and ſad oppreſſions in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land both in conſcience, and the eſtates of moſt of this poor Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſadly being ſince ſet forth, that the Parliament of both Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the moſt mature, and ſerious Counſells thought no way fit to remedy the three Nations, but to aſſiſt one another in Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, who had left the protection of his people, withdrew from his Parliament, and like a Butcher rather then a Prince of bowells and affection raiſeth Armies in every part of the Nation, of the moſt deſperate Malignant, and Popiſh ſpirits, to deſtroy and ruine the Parliaments of both Nations, and after a ſeven years war with the expence of an unſpeakable treaſure of riches and blood, the moſt precious blood of thouſands of Proteſtants, yea Saints, God having given us victory over his Armies and Forces, as a juſt determination of the cauſe we appeal'd to him to vindicate; yet as a man of blood, while all eſſaies and meanswere uſing for peace, by his inſtrument and commiſſions, raiſeth a ſecond war in both Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if the Nation had not drunk deep enough of that ſad cup, and without any remorſe, gives new Commiſſion to <hi>Ormond</hi> to be ſure to make peace with the Iriſh Rebells on any terms and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, though not one Propoſition for the good of this Nation could be heartily conſented unto by him; and yet becauſe we would try all means, followed him up and down with Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſending Commiſſioners ſometimes two hundred miles, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a hundred, all to beg his aſſent to what we had fought for, crouching and cringing as if we were ſtill his ſlaves, and he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd his negative vote by our victories; and yet no one Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any concernment after all reiterated eſſaies, that might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us in our liberties, or Religion granted, but apparently found all the waies uſed for to gaine him, were turn'd into deſignes of dangerous conſequence againſt this Nation eſpecially: neither in his moſt retired and ſolitary condition, could any perceive the leaſt ſenſe of remorſe from him, for all the blood ſhed in the three Nations, delighting commonly in private to diſcourſe of the wars,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115748:11"/> and how many were ſlain, and laughing at every fatall expreſſion, which every Chriſtian heart can never ſenſibly enough lament, and yet this man muſt be untouch't, and all the blood as utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, as it was freely and violently ſpilt on the ground, and thought ſufficiently ſatisfied for, if he would but ſet his hand to a few Propoſitions, though loathing it in his heart: and the ſame things wee propoſed in the beginning of the war, and yet we could not obtain that favour from him, freely, and with ſenſe to grant thoſe juſt deſires we had got by the blood of our friends, and the overthrow of all his Armies. Let the Committee of Eſtates ſpeak from their conſciences, and hearken to the ſecret whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of their own ſpirits, and tell us plainly, whether ever there was any hope of ever ſetling Reformation, and liberty by that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whether ſuch crimes found in any one perſon on earth, were not meritorious of the utmoſt puniſhment; or whether divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and vengeance would not have followed this Nation, had we ſpared that perſons life, with the careleſſe oblivion of all that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood ſhed meerly by his Commiſſion, and for his will; and doubtleſſe had not God raiſed up the ſpirits of a remnant to doe Juſtice in ſo publique, and glorious a manner, and ſo have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Gods judgment on us, the cry of blood was ſo loud in Gods ears, that God would ſtretch forth ſome immediate hand and have done it himſelf, with terrour and amazement to all the Nations. And had there been any probable hope of better things from him, yet the good that we ſhould have got by him, would be nothing to the weight of blood that would lie on this Nation unſatisfied for to procure judgements: But what hope was there, was his conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution or affections either to Epiſcopacy or Malignancy, altered or abated; had he any lower thought of himſelf and Prerogative, was not the Queen as nearly related to him as ever, did he not as much hate the Covenant as ever, did he want any thing but pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and oportunity to react his old principles? Let us not trifle in theſe ſerious concernments; politicall complements will not ſave Kingdoms, the blood-thirſty man ſhall not live out half his daies, ſaith holy Writ, neither is it murther, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> execute the murtherer, but reaſon, and juſtice, there is no reaſon in nature or divinity, that tells us, that Kings are of ſuch pure and refined fleſh, that they muſt in no cauſe be let blood: what hath been done by the Parliament
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115748:11"/> of England on that man of blood, Heaven, and Earth hath and will witneſſe unto, and vve doubt not novv juſtice is done (though it ſhould be but from a raiſ'd zeale as <hi>Phineas</hi> act vvas, yet the perſon being the deſerving ſubject of it) the plague ſhall be ſtaid.</p>
            <p>And yet however we have all this reaſon and neceſſity for that Act, with many eminent providences of God to ſhew concurring with, and following it, yet we free our Brethren from the guilt of the blood, and wiſh heartily that they may be as free from the conſequences of their politike compliances with the late King and his Son, as we are before God of the crime and fault of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably memorable Act; they have (if they would ſpeak out) more reaſon to thank theſe inſtruments then charge them who have cut off the viſible root of their and our miſeries, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they nor we know how to make a good uſe of, and be true to our Covenant and conſciences; but though the root be cut down as rotten, they intend to preſerve the moſt naturall branch to graffe on the old ſtock of Malignancy, that what the one could not do, the other may if poſſible, effect.</p>
            <p>But let things be but accounted right, was it not better to do an Act of Iuſtice at once, in taking away the Kings life, then to have left him dead while he lived, and to have crucified him all dayes of his life with Papers and Pamphlets, with reproaches and continuall repreſentations of his unworthy and bloody actions, and to have wiſh'd the ſame end? yea, onely to have let him live to ſee his miſery, and to have beheld thoſe actings, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the greateſt and higheſt affronts, and worſe then death; it would be a great controverſie to determine whether the King thought his impriſonment and reſtraint more infamous and cruell, or his death: if in the firſt, the hope of an oportunity of revenge did not refreſh and comfort him, certainly it muſt needs be more honeſt and juſt before God and man, for wicked and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious acts to cut him off from his Kingdome, then by degrees to complement him out of it, and let him live to ſee it; in the one ſhines juſtice, in the other baſeneſſe and deceit: Had he reigned with all the qualifications and limitations we could for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent have put on his Government, we had been ruined, and had he not reign'd, we had let him ſee his beſt ſelf dead as a King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115748:12"/> he died as a man, which is a double death, and ſo had as it were ſtrangled him, a more ignoble death then beheading. The Committee of Eſtates might well remember on whom both their Kirk and State, and our Parliament did often on more then ſhrewd ſuppoſitions, lay the death of King <hi>James,</hi> the loſſe of Rochell, &amp;c. and with one voice, ye at the laſt perſonall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Iſle of Wight, did law the whole weight and charge of all the blood ſpilt in the three Nations directly on the Kings head, and either it muſt lie on him or both Nations; and was it fit in conſcience that ſuch a head ſhould ſtand on his body, which was full of ſo much innocent blood? let juſtice and reaſon bluſh, and Traytors and Murtherers, Parricides and Patricides put on white garments, and rejoyce as innocent ones, if this man ſhould eſcape the hands of juſtice and puniſhment: Yea, let <hi>Montroſſe</hi> himſelf, whom the Kirk calls a monſter of men, a child of the Devill, clap hands, and be canoniz'd for a Saint, who rid but poſt, as it were, (and for a little time) through Scotland, deſtroying and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in compariſon of the late <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> who hath been the maine and only cauſe of the death of thouſands, ſhall I ſay, milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men ever ſince his reigne in England Scotland, France and Ireland, Nature, Reaſon, Religion, did cry loud for vengeance, and I had almoſt ſaid, and I may ſpeak it without paſſion, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had eclipſed, yea, loſt the brighteſt beam of his divine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice that ever ſhined on this lower world, if he had not ſome way or other brought that perſon to ſome eminent and preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall puniſhment, and that way which God acted by was the moſt eminent and glorious: But enough of this, they are ſatisfied, and ſo are we, and if honeſt and juſt actings now follow, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have cauſe to repent of that act.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing he taxeth them withall, is that they have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Son King with proviſo's, robbing him of all right, &amp;c. I ſhall ſay little againſt the juſtneſſe of that proceeding, if they will have a King they had need provide firſt for themſelves, yet there is much which may be objected, and to ſpeak truth, as what ever they may expect from their new King will be but out of deſigne granted, and untill he get the Kingdome, ſo their actings ſeem to be but a beſpeaking of a refuſall, and though the things they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound be never ſo neceſſary and juſt, yet he hath his negative voice
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115748:12"/> and power to deny them, and yet be their King notwithſtanding. It had been a more faire way and leſſe ſubject to miſpriſion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, to have ſent their conditions firſt, e're they proclaimed him King, and ſo to have let him know he injoyes not the Kingdome by ſucceſſion, but by election, and compact on ſuch conditions, rather then firſt to declare him King, give him full right, and then put conditions without which he muſt not expect to be King; that his Kingly right and power is involved in their conditions, not in any naturall right of ſucceſſion or heirſhip, and as much as to tell him plainly, you have no right nor title to the Kingdome of Scotland without you grant theſe terms which we think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>, and though we have proclaimed you King, will not own you as a King, but really and implicitely depoſe you, and ſo found your power onely in election and theſe qualifications, which had they expreſt, they laid down the right and true grounds of all power in Kings and other Magiſtrates which flowes immediately from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that mutuall compact and agreement that is between them, without which they are but Uſurpers and Tyrants; and this is virtually and truly the conſtruction of their carriage to the King, though very commendable and laudable, and if they have a King that will not heartily comply with them in their own juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, they may think upon a ſecond defenſive war in Scotland; yet it's a hard caſe, that they muſt travel up and down on the wil of a young Malignant, to beg confirmation of Propoſitions abſolutely neceſſary for their own ſafety, and the eſtate, and wiſdom, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of a whole Nation hang on the <hi>placet</hi> of a creature of their own making. They may have time to ſee, and feel yet, what a ſnare they are brought into by that one ſudden act of proclaiming him King: For, notwithſtanding he ſhould grant all their deſires for the preſent, and come in as their King, and royallize it among them; and they as they expreſſe it <hi>p.</hi> 20. ſhould imbrace him on theſe termes, do they imagine whom they lay in their boſome? the Son of a bloody Father, Heire to an entail'd curſe, more certain then to his Kingdome; train'd up himſelf in blood all his dayes, one that is ſet up to follow on where his Father left off; one that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuckt in any other principles, but prerogative, and tyranny, bred up under Biſhops and Ceremonies, which the ayre of Scotland ſeems to have a naturall antipathy unto; one whom they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115748:13"/> ſee is far off from hearkening to any ſound counſell or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice but of thoſe whom both Kingdoms have proclaimed Traitors; who hates the Covenant, and can never take it, but to take them in their own ſhare. Alas, who knowes the conſequence? who, as ſoon as they receive him muſt ſet him on horſe-back, and ingage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Brethren of England, who have helped and ſuccoured them in their diſtreſſe, and fight the old quarrell only in the name of <hi>Charles the ſecond.</hi> My pen trembles to write; and do not the hearts of the Committee of Eſtates, and the godly party in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhake, for fear he may ſeal, and ſigne to theſe Propoſitions? Let him have an Army, he will ſoon be Generall, and once a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, his young head will carry him far enough. Alas! to ſee Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Ceremonies in Scotland again, to behold the old Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants triumphing on the ruines of the Kirk, what a dolefull ſtory would that be! Doth not every godly eye foreſee this in the dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the day? Hath <hi>Chaales Stuart</hi> learnt ſo much goodneſſe and honeſty, to forſake all his Fathers beſt Friends, to be quite out of correſpondency, and affections to his Mother, and Coſins the Popiſh and Malignant Party in all the three Nations, onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf to live under the good and wholſom Diſcipline of the Kirk of Scotland? Or can it poſſibly be conceived, that they ſhould entertain him without his train, either at preſent, or ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly to follow after him? Ah poor Scotland, once the terror to Epiſcopacy and Malignancy, the firſt promoters of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and art thou at laſt faine to take the grand Enemy of Church and State into thy boſome, and doſt beg but to enjoy him? Art forc'd to ſeek thy peace in thy enemies quarters? God forbid: theſe ſighs wil be aggravated in honeſt hearts, if ever ſuch a change ſhould come to paſſe. Do not they know that God will viſit the ſins of the fathers on their children, eſpecially the ſins of thoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents which have been perſecutors of the Church, and hinderers of reformation, and have unnaturally ſpilt the blood of Saints; and moſt eſpecially when the children have likewiſe been acceſſories and actors in the ſame deſigne? How ſad is it, that when God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning Kings, &amp; caſting ſhame upon Princes as the great enemies of his Church, Scotland ſhould be ſetting them up, and him that never had yet his face towards Sion. This ſtory is too ſad to be long inſiſted on. And therefore on the other ſide, if he ſhould deny to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115748:13"/> grant theſe their deſires, or pick, and chooſe, and propoſe terms of his own, as his Father did with both Kingdoms formerly, what a ſnare will yet lie on them, that they ſhould not let their King raign, without proſtrating his Conſcence and Honor (as he thinks) unto their deſires? And may not <hi>Montroſſe</hi> juſtly tax them with proclaiming him <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Proviſoes, &amp;c?</hi> And whereas they may ſay, they have given him right <hi>ad rem</hi> to the Kingdom, but not <hi>in re</hi> to the lawful and actual exerciſe of his Power, it will not ſerve the turn; for it's as good never proclaim him <hi>King,</hi> as not let him raign; yea to proclaim him <hi>King,</hi> and deny him the exerciſe of his Kingly Power, is clearly to depoſe him before he comes to raign, depoſing being nothing elſe but excluding Kings from the exerciſe of that power they were formerly inveſted with: And let the world judg who deals more candidly with the King, the <hi>Parliament of England,</hi> or the <hi>Committee of Eſtates;</hi> the one tells him plainly, <hi>He hath no Right, but what he gets by the Sword;</hi> and the other proclaims his Right, and will not let him exerciſe it, without either he give them their own terms, or conquer them. Kings uſe not to paſs by ſuch courteſies, they take deeper impreſſion then moſt imagine; he that is not worthy, nor fit to exerciſe his office, it's pity he ſhould have the name; neither do Kings love to have their pictures drawing when they are dying. Our Brethren are yet treating with the old Enemy, and muſt pump what they can from his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, with continual hazard, while we are trying how to propagate our Liberties and Advantages to the utmoſt, and under a full ſail of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: We might have been all this while treating, and have given as much time to our Enemies to plot, as we to ſettle; but God will countenance and proſper the moſt ſincere and plain honeſt dealings; and if we periſh, (which would be more ſad otherwiſe) yet it's in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our duty, and as ſeeds of a more glorious <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one thing more in the concluſion of this <hi>Declaration,</hi> wherein they ſay, That they <hi>hope there is none in that Land, or if any be found ſo baſe, fooliſh, and treacherous, as to harken to the vain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of</hi> James Graham, <hi>&amp;c. they do declare all ſuch as joyn with him, or his Adherents, in Arms, to be guilty of high Treaſon, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if their <hi>King</hi> joyn with him? he is truly proclaimed a <hi>Traytor:</hi> Nay, what if the <hi>King</hi> gave him that <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to be <hi>Lieut. Governor,</hi> and <hi>Capt. General for his Majeſty, &amp;c.</hi> which Paper expreſſing this <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> they ſay, pag. 11. They <hi>have burnt by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115748:14"/> common hangman at the Croſs at Edinburgh:</hi> And have they not then burnt the <hi>Kings Commiſſion?</hi> and <hi>in an idem,</hi> and repreſentation, held forth what they mean to do with his perſon, if he prove the Author of the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and be found to joyn with <hi>Montroſſe.</hi> Its accounted in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and I think in the <hi>Laws of England,</hi> That <hi>what is done to the picture, or publique repreſentation of a perſon, is much more done to the perſon it ſelf:</hi> for if they vent their malice to the dead image, much more would they to the living perſon: The image and portraiture of <hi>Kings</hi> are not ſeen in the lineaments of their faces or bodies, drawn by the mixture of colours, and the fancy of a painter, but in their publique Repreſentations, in their Commiſſions and Grants, wherein they appear in their office; for elſe as fair and authentique, grave and majeſtique faces may be drawn better to repreſent nature, then in the beſt of them.</p>
            <p>But all theſe things, formerly excepted againſt, are but miſtakes, and politique Evaſions by the <hi>Committee of Eſtates:</hi> Let us now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (waving all perſonal and particular Engagements, (and ſuppoſing an error in our Proceedings) and ſeriouſly conſider together what may unite us, or rather recover the fence of our Union, and reciprocal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments: We are not conſcious of ever ſinning, or tranſgreſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Priviledges of Scotland,</hi> (though we are loath to repeat their Actions in <hi>England,</hi> and concerning it,) if we have offended or done any thing againſt their real <hi>Priviledges,</hi> we ſhall humbly acknowledg it with great ſence; and wherein the Union hath been broken on our ſide, ſhall endeavor to make it up with ſatisfaction: but if our Brethren think that the <hi>King</hi> will unite more then the Covenant, we are ſorry we muſt not only diſſent, but differ: There is no means left to preſerve theſe two <hi>Nations</hi> in the eye of Reaſon, but their Union together in common principles, (waving the particular miſcarriages of both <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> And how ever we may imagine, and make a fancy of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> equally to be oppoſed with <hi>Malignants,</hi> we ſhall find, and they, with a witneſs, that the one is poſſible, and eaſily curable, by a ſtrict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the honeſt and prevailing party, the other engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both.</p>
            <p>There is no difference between our Brethren and us of moment, but about Kingly Government, and the perſons which muſt raign, againſt which we have upon juſt Reaſons proteſted; and it will be hard for them to bear the ſingle burthen of that Monarchy, which expects to be maintained by the three Nations.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115748:14"/>
            <p>And though we dare not diſhonor our Cauſe and Nation, to beg a Union, and their Correſpondence, (which yet will be both honorable and ſafe to both Nations,) and ſcorn to ſtoop the grandeur of this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> ſo much as to entreat them into the conſideration of their own condition, as they do mechanically follow their and our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (called their <hi>King;</hi>) yet we ſhall be glad to renew any ways of amity and affableneſs with that Nation, and ſhall account it a high and ſpecial favour from Heaven, if he give us wiſdom to joyn our Intereſt together, in the preſervation of the true and right ends of the Covenant, which will elſe be forgotten among us, and to ſettle <hi>Religion</hi> againſt theſe which may be truly called <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and Government contrary to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and moſt proper for <hi>Reformation,</hi> in the ſetling of an able and powerful <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and purging <hi>Congregations:</hi> In a word, the countenancing all the ways of godlineſs, which we have an happy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity now to effect, the principle <hi>Obstante</hi> removed out of the way (upon whoſe voyce we put the determination of the welfare both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi>) and if our diſſenting Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> would but lay aſide private and ſpecial Intereſts, and minde the publique, and take advantages of Providences, how ſoon might they have both <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>State</hi> reformed, even unto the utmoſt period of all deſires: If there be any defect in ſetting up <hi>Preſbyterial Government,</hi> in taking care for the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> I wiſh it may not prove to lie on the Miniſters themſelves, who, out of Principles of Royalty, or private Engagements do not only withdraw from, but ſpeak againſt this preſent <hi>Government,</hi> and the righteous Conſtitution of it. But if our Brethren wil wave the Covenant, and make the King the <hi>medium</hi> of our union, we have done our duty. Let the Iſſue be tryed, we ſhal venter on the ſame Providence, maintain the ſame Cauſe, however the change be in perſons and ſpirits: Reformation of Religion in Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, Civil Liberties, a univerſal Propagation of the Goſpel being our end. Let them ſee if <hi>K. Charls</hi> be the fit Inſtrument to effect theſe honeſt things. If the <hi>Parlia. of England</hi> follow not the moſt adequate and beſt means to that end, <hi>viz.</hi> of the ſetting up pure <hi>Religion,</hi> and juſt <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> after all the Mercies they have enjoyed from Heaven; and if the <hi>Kingdom of Scotland</hi> joyn not with them on theſe Grounds, waving all other conſiderations, they will both be <hi>Anathema Maranatha:</hi> And if Reaſon and Religion cannot decide the Controverſie between Brethren, the Sword will never do it, eſpecially when enemies ſhal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it, but endanger the ruine of both. If our Brethren will not hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115748:15"/> to terms of Peace and Love, but, beſides their own danger and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, will embrace the Enemy of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> not only to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ, but raign among them, they muſt give us leave to ſecure <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> as well as we can, and once more leave it to <hi>Providence</hi> to umpire: Only it will be ſad, that while we are trifling about names, and <hi>punctilioes</hi> of things, our common Enemy ſhould grow ſtrong, and deſtroy us. I have nothing elſe to add, but to retire my ſelf into my Cloſet, and bewail the Diviſions of both <hi>Nations</hi> about Ceremonies and Shadows, while their and our Enemies laugh and deſign; and to lament for our ignorance, who think that a <hi>Malignant King</hi> can be brought in to raign without a <hi>Malignant Intereſt,</hi> and that we ſhould be all the days of our lives pruning the branches, and cutting them off, and yet be ſtrengthning and fatning the root of our miſeries. I end with prayer to the Almighty, That both <hi>Nations</hi> may have a true ſence of the Glorious Actings of God theſe laſt years, and may know the true and proper Intereſt of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and both unite once more in common <hi>Principles,</hi> That the good Work of <hi>Reformation</hi> ſo bleſſedly begun, notwithſtanding the <hi>Malignant Parties</hi> in the three <hi>Nations,</hi> may receive no obſtruction in its perfection by theſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to intend the growth and glory of it, that while we are ſtriving who ſhall have the Shell, <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Malignancy</hi> may not get the Kernel, and recover their loſt Intereſts by our private and particular Diſcontents.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
